A Guide to the Bradley T. Johnson Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #5594
Bradley T. Johnson Papers 1676-1937
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
5594
ca. 4000 items
Mrs. Bradley T. Johnson
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection is on loan from Mrs. Bradley T. Johnson, 510 17th Street, Charlottesville, Virginia. It was placed in the Library on 21 May 1957.
Biographical Sketch of Bradley T. Johnson
Bradley T. Johnson(1829-1903) was born in Frederick, Maryland, son of Charles Worthington Johnson and Eleanor Murdock (Tyler) Johnson, grandson of Colonel Baker Tyler Johnson of the Continental Army. He took a B.A. at Princeton(1849), studied law and was admitted to the bar in Frederick in 1851. On June 25, 1851 he married Jane Claudia Saunders of North Carolina. Johnson served as Maryland State's Attorney, Chairman of the Maryland State Democratic Committee, and delegate to both National Conventions of 1860. He was instrumental in the formation of " The Maryland Line, " a regiment of Marylanders who chose to fight for the South, and was elected their Colonel in 1862. On June 28, 1864, he was commissioned brigadier general, partly on the strength of a long standing recommendation from General T. J. Jackson. In the last days of the war he commanded cavalry under Wade Hampton and Jubal Early. After the war, Johnson practiced law in Richmond and served in the Virginia Senate (1875-1879). From 1879 to 1890 he practiced in Baltimore. He died in Amelia, Virginia, in 1903. Among his published works are a life of Washington (1894) and A Memoir of the Life and Public Service of Joseph E. Johnston.
Scope and Content
The papers of Bradley T. Johnson consist of ca. 4000 items covering the years 1676 to 1937, and are primarily the personal correspondence of the members of three families: Johnson, Rutherfoord and Saunders. By far the greatest number of letters and documents concern the affairs of the Johnson family and Bradley T. Johnson during the period 1840-1880. The collection includes a great number of letters to Bradley T. Johnson from his mother, Eleanor Murdock (Tyler) Johnson, and his wife, Jane Claudia (Saunders) Johnson. Items of particular interest include: copies of letters from George Washington to Thomas Johnson relative to Thomas Johnson's appointment to the United States Supreme Court and letters to General Bradley T. Johnson from Jubal A. Early, Joseph E. Johnston, Thomas J. Jackson, Jefferson Davis, Wade Hampton, J. S. Mosby, W. H. Fitzhugh Lee, Henry Adams and Theodore Roosevelt.
In addition to correspondence, the collection contains unsigned speeches and essays dealing with contemporary (antebellum) political issues and elections as well as newspaper clippings, deeds, documents and memorabila. In particular, there is a substantial number of items pertaining to Bradley T. Johnson's formation of the First Maryland Regiment, C. S. A., " The Maryland Line, " and its affairs during the Civil War and afterwards as a veterans' organization. There are a number of letters written by John C. Rutherfoord and Bradley T. Johnson's son, B. Saunders Johnson, to their respective families while the two were students at the University of Virginia, the former before and the latter after the Civil War.
Organization
Boxes 1 through 4 contain correspondence filed chronologically. The next three boxes contain speeches, essays, financial and Civil War papers. The last box contains empty envelopes.
Container List
- Correspondence of Thomas Johnson and Baker Johnson, 1775-1800 (Box Box 1)
- [Letter of gratitude from the Maryland Assembly] to [?], 1779 Nov 22 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of William Johnson and Thomas Johnson, 1812-1818 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of Eleanor Murdock Johnson and [William] Johnson, 1823-1827 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of Mrs. Ann Roy, 1829-1830 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Saunders, Rutherfoord, and Johnson families, 1832-1836 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Stevenson and Saunders families, 1838-1841 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence primarily between John C. Rutherfoord and his family, 1842-1843 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson and of the Saunders and Rutherfoord families, 1844-1846; 3 folders (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence primarily between John C. Rutherfoord and his father, 1847 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Rutherfoord family, 1848-1850; 3 folders (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Rutherfoord family, 1851-1855; 5 folders (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Johnson, Rutherfoord, Saunders and Roy families, 1856 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily of the Rutherfoord family, 1857 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily of Bradley T. Johnson, 1858 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence of John C. Rutherfoord and Bradley T. Johnson, 1859-1860; 2 folders (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence re: "The Maryland Line", 1861-1862; 2 folders (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence of John C. Rutherfoord and Bradley T. Johnson, 1863 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily of John C. Rutherfoord, 1864 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson and John C. Rutherfoord, 1865 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily of Bradley T. Johnson including a copy of a letter from U. S. Grant recommending Johnson's release, 1866 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence of Edward McCrady, Bradley T. Johnson, and the Saunders and Rutherfoord families, 1867-1871 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily of Bradley T. Johnson, 1872-1873 (Box Box 2)
- ALS, J. E. Johnston to Bradley T. Johnson, 1874 May 4 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence principally from Saunders Johnson, a student at U. Va., to his father, Bradley T. Johnson, 1874 (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily from Saunders Johnson to his parents, 1875 Jan-May (Box Box 2)
- Correspondence primarily from Saunders Johnson to his parents, 1875 June-Dec (Box Box 3)
- J. A. Early to Bradley T. Johnson, 1875 Sept-Oct (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence of the Johnson family, 1876-1880; 5 folders (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson and Edward McCrady, 1881 (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson, 1882-1888 (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson, 1890-1893 (Box Box 3)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson, 1894-1900 (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence primarily of Bradley T. Johnson and Bradley S. Johnson, 1901-1904 (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence of the Johnson family, 1905-1937; 2 folders (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence of Bradley S. Johnson primarily with his parents (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence of Bradley T. Johnson (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence of the Johnson family, 2 folders (Box Box 4)
- Correspondence of the Johnson family, 2 folders (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence of the Rutherfoord family (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence of the Saunders family (Box Box 5)
- Correspondence of the Stevenson family (Box Box 5)
- Notebook of Thomas Johnson, Jr., 1770 (Box Box 5)
- Ms, Speech by Thomas Johnson praising George Washington, fragment of eulogy of George Washington by Thomas Johnson, 1788 Feb.22 (Box Box 5)
- AMs, "Political Paper" in defense of the Federal Government, by [ Thomas Johnson], 1800 (Box Box 5)
- AMs, Speech: "Politics 1806 Against Madison 1st Election" by [ Thomas Johnson] (Box Box 5)
- AMs, Speech: "Against Madison" by [ Thomas Johnson], 1808 (Box Box 5)
- Drafts of Political Speeches, Essays [ Thomas Johnson], 1800-1809 (Box Box 5)
- Speeches: "Politics-1812" [ Thomas Johnson] (Box Box 5)
- Printed Periodical "Rights of Man - by John Winter", 1800 (Box Box 5)
- Essays, Speeches of J. C. Rutherfoord, 1845 (Box Box 5)
- John Rutherfoord Speech, 1885 (Box Box 5)
- Essays, Speeches of B. T. Johnson, 1847-1849 (Box Box 5)
- B. T. Johnson Printed Writings, 1860-1894 (Box Box 5)
- 2 leaves from a life of Washington by B. T. Johnson, 1894 (Box Box 5)
- Bradley Johnson, Jr.'s essay "The Spanish War", 1898 (Box Box 5)
- Nannie P. Rutherfoord's essay "The Life of Byron", n. d. (Box Box 5)
- Memoirs of Ann Rutherfoord of the James River and Kanawha Canal (Box Box 5)
- Miscellaneous manuscripts, fragments of essays, writings by unknown authors, n. d. (Box Box 5)
- Bradley Johnson's Christmas stories written for his children, 1893-1894 (Box Box 5)
- Poetry, n. d. (Box Box 5)
- Eulogies, Memorials, 1890-1917 (Box Box 5)
- Marriage Record and Birth Record, family of Richard Johnson, 1676-1680 (Box Box 6)
- "The Answer of Christopher Moyer to the Bill of Complaint of Baker Johnson", 1771 Mar. 22 (Box Box 6)
- Indenture: Thomas Beaty to Baker Johnson, 1778 Aug. 24 (Box Box 6)
- Page from business records, 1725-1790 (Box Box 6)
- Account booklet, financial records, 1826-1850 (Box Box 6)
- Surveyors reports, 1701-1826 (Box Box 6)
- Wills, including a statement of funds of the estate of William Johnson, 1881-1911 (Box Box 6)
- Trust Deeds, Indentures and related agreements, some referring to the ownership and sale of slaves, 1828-1911 (Box Box 6)
- Legal Documents, Subpoenas, Court Decisions, Land Title, Contract of Sale, ca.1867-1914 (Box Box 6)
- Genealogies and notes for geneologies, including those for the Booths, Alexanders, Todds, Roys and Seddons and Johnsons of Yarmouth (Box Box 6)
- The Georgetown Weekly Ledger, 1792 Jan. 21 (Box Box 6)
- Frederick-Town Herald, 1808-1819 (Box Box 6)
- Newspaper Clippings, a large number relating to the death of Wade Hampton and Dr. George Ben Johnson (Box Box 6)
- Educational records, 1822-1875 (Box Box 6)
- "Belles Lettres Class Book" belonging to Nannie S. Rutherfoord, 1875 (Box Box 6)
- "House Book" of expenses (household), 1860-1863 (Box Box 6)
- Maps, 1887, 1907, n.d. (Box Box 6)
- Religious booklets, n. d. (Box Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Papers, including plans for a Memorial to B. T. Johnson, n. d. (Box Box 6)
- Bradley T. Johnson and The Maryland Line: Proclamations, Orders and Battle Accounts, 1861-1888 (Box Box 7)
- Election results for Commander of Maryland Line, 1864 Feb 6 (Box Box 7)
- Military financial records: Requisitions and supplies, 1862-1865 (Box Box 7)
- Civil War: Miscellaneous Documents, n. d. (Box Box 7)
- Charter for an organization of Confederate Veterans, n. d. (Box Box 7)
- Documents relating to various civic and philanthropic societies, 1879-1913 (Box Box 7)
- Receipts for deposits with Confederate Memorial Literary Society, 1902-1906 (Box Box 7)
- Mr. and Mrs. Bradley T. Johnson: Honors, Appointments, Invitations, 1871-1919 (Box Box 7)
- Materials relating to B. T. Johnson's Senate race, 1874 Sept (Box Box 7)
- Recommendations of Bradley T. Johnson for Assistant Attorney General, 1893-1898 (Box Box 7)
- Family Financial Records - Civil War Period, 1859 (Box Box 7)
- Financial Papers: Inventories, Promissory Notes, Receipts, 1866-1899 (Box Box 7)
- Papers relating to the Bankruptcy of William J. Saunders, 1867 (Box Box 7)
- Oyster Industry Papers (Box Box 7)
- Financial Papers: Receipts, Insurance Policies, Stock Brokers' Reports, 1900-1926 (Box Box 7)
- Souvenir Ribbons and Memorabilia (Box Box 7)
- Documents relating to the R.M.S. "Titanic," the S.S. "Lapland," and other sailing information (Box Box 7)
- Tourist cards, Booklets, Souvenirs, n. d. (Box Box 7)
- Post Cards, n. d. (Box Box 7)
- Empty Envelopes (Box Box 8)
- Deed of property in South Carolina between Frederick W. Ford, Bradley T. Johnson, and William J. Saunders, 1867 Feb. 10 (Box Oversize)
- Bradley T. Johnson's credentials as Electore for the State of Maryland, 1884 (Box Oversize)
- The Spectator, 1934 Sept 21 (Box Oversize)
- Certificate of gratitude to Mrs. Bradley T. Johnson from The Society of the Army and Navy of the Confederate States (Box Oversize)
- Photograph of Caldwell A. Alphin, n. d. (Box Oversize)